Good evening!
Let’s talk about Finnish
language for a moment.
More specifically,
let’s focus on the phonemes
of the Finnish language.
In Finnish,
there are eight vowels:
a, e, i, o,
u, y, ä and ö.
Each of these vowels is always
spelled with the same letter,
so when you read
this symbol, ⟨o⟩,
it is always
pronounced /o/.
No exceptions.
Sometimes there can be two
of these letters in row,
like this: ⟨oo⟩.
This means a long vowel.
Basically you just stretch
the vowel a bit: /oː/.
The length is
not exact science.
What is important is that
the vowel sound does not change.
For instance, it does
not become /oʊ/.
If you pronounce the long
vowel as a diphthong,
your foreign background
is exposed sooner –
than you can close your mouth.
Thus, Finnish has short
vowels and long vowels.
a, aa, e, ee, i, ii, o, oo,
u, uu, y, yy, ä, ää, ö, öö.
When two different vowels
come in sequence,
like in the word “koe”,
the two vowels are both
pronounced individually.
“Koe”.
In real life though,
Finnish has many diphtongs,
but these are spontaneous
observations rather than rules,
and it is perfectly
fine to ignore them.
We can also ignore
the long vowels,
because it is basically
just the same vowel –
repeated twice in a row,
making it twice as long.
As a general rule,
the vowel sound is unaffected
by the consonant –
that precedes or follows it.
If you nasalize the vowel
right before a consonant,
your Swedish background
becomes immediately apparent.
The rest of phonemes
are consonants.
The only trill
consonant is r.
The approximants
are v, l and j.
The nasal consonants
are n and m,
but there is also
the ng sound /ŋ/,
which is an exception,
because it is the only
sound in Finnish –
that is denoted by a
sequence of two letters –
and does not have
its own symbol.
The fricative consonants
are s and h.
The phoneme f occurs
in loan words,
but it is not natively
a part of Finnish.
There is just
one sibilant,
and it is the voiceless
alveolar sibilant, /s/.
The post-alveolar sibilant /ʃ/
occurs in some loan words,
and there is actually a letter
in the Finnish alphabet for it,
but most Finns cannot pronounce
this sound without practice.
The sibilant sounds
are never voiced.
Most Finns cannot even pronounce
sounds like /z/ and /ʒ/ –
without practice.
If you use those sounds,
the listener immediately guesses
your background is Slavic.
All of the above
are like vowels,
in that they can be
either short or long.
For example, keno, kenno,
kisa, kissa, tuli, and tulli –
are different words,
These six words all
have different meanings –
that have nothing in common.
Again, the length
is not exact science;
as long as it is clear
from your speech,
that the phoneme is
slightly longer than normal,
it counts as a long phoneme.
It is important to note —
that it is entirely
a timing issue,
not an emphasis
or stress issue.
Well, there are no words
with a long v or a long j,
but if there were,
all Finns would know
how to pronounce them.
Finally there are
plosive consonants:
The unvoiced k, p, and t,
and their voiced counterparts,
g, b, and d.
However, b and g sounds only
occur in words of foreign origin,
and some dialects do not
recognize the voiced plosives at all.
In Finnish, the plosives
are not aspirated,
so instead of khaptheeni,
you would say kapteeni.
If you aspirate your consonants,
the listener immediately guesses
your background is English.
The plosives can also
be short or long.
For example, kuka, kukka,
mato, matto, rapu and rappu –
are all different words,
with meanings that
have nothing in common.
Because the plosive consonants
are characterized –
by a sudden sound that
follows a silence,
the difference between
a short and long plosive –
is how long the air
is held before released.
Finally there is the
glottal stop, /ʔ/.
This sound occurs sometimes
before a vowel –
when the speaker
wants to be clear –
where the syllable break
or word break is,
or to emphasize
the beginning of a word.
Example, “mä en halua”
means I don’t want,
but “mä’en halua” means
I really don’t want.
Sometimes the exact quality
of the consonant can change –
depending on the
following phonemes.
For example, if an "n" letter
is followed by a "p" letter,
almost everyone pronounces
it as "m" instead of "n".
For example, "kumpa"
instead of "kunpa".
If the "n" letter is followed
by a "k" letter instead,
most readers pronounce
it as "ng",
for example "ongko"
instead of "onko".
The “h” letter can be pronounced
in a number of different ways –
depending on the
surrounding vowels.
Examples: “pehmeä”, “lahja”, “pihvi”.
Each of these were articulated
in a different part of the mouth.
These three phonemes are called
allophones for the phoneme “h”,
and most native speakers are
not even aware of the differences.
Again, these are spontaneously
arising phenomena rather than rules.
Note, that unlike in
Hebrew and English,
if there is a “h” in the text,
it’s a consonant, and it is
always pronounced as “h”.
There are no silent letters in Finnish.
There is one curious exception,
namely gemination.
In some cases,
a consonant is pronounced long
even if it’s written short.
For example, instead of “syö hernekeittoa”
you would say “syö hhernekkeittoa”.
I’m not totally sure why this happens.
It just does.
It is not something that could cause
misunderstandings either way,
but a curious detail nonetheless.
Note that you can’t just go randomly
duplicating phonemes.
If you pronounced “älä menekkään”
as “älämmenekkään”,
the listener would have to do –
a double take to understand
what you just said.
A little bit about timings.
Different languages have different ideas
about how speech is timed.
In English and Swedish,
for example,
the time between consecutive
stressed syllables is fairly constant.
In French, each syllable takes
roughly the same time.
In Japanese, each syllable also
takes roughly the same time,
except that syllables with a long vowel are
pronounced twice as long as regular syllables.
But Finnish is not like that.
Finnish is different.
Basically, each phoneme,
represented by a single letter,
takes a constant time.
Long phonemes are represented by two letters,
and they take twice the time.
There are a few exceptions though.
Again, things that just rise
spontaneously from practice.
So, to recap:
Eight vowels,
and about twelve consonants.
Phonetically Finnish is quite
a simple language.
This is the phonetic vocabulary
that a Finnish person has,
when they speak
any foreign language.
As I explained
in another video,
whichever phonetic background a person
has from their native language –
largely determines what
kind of accent they have –
when speaking another language.
The simplicity of Finnish phonetics
contributes to –
the quite recognizable accent
that Finnish people often have –
when they speak a language –
that has phonetically a
significantly different makeup,
such as English.
We may be revisiting this topic
soon in another video.
Stay tuned, and have
a shalom in your life.